How do you find a winning product idea
to build and to bootstrap into a
potential business? Well, you know, most
advice that you'll hear out there is
going to point you in the direction of
being opportunistic, right? You got to
identify hot market trends or you got to
find an underserved niche or you know
you got to go through the motions of
prevalidating your ideas and you know um
and and make sure that you're really
sure that there are going to be paying
customers for this or that idea before
you ever write a line of code. We've
heard all that. I've lived all that for
years as a bootstrapped business owner.
But you know after over a decade of
following that line of thinking the
being opportunistic about finding
product ideas and choosing which ones to
pursue as my business. This year I've
sort of come full circle back around to
a much simpler approach and it's the one
we we've known and and heard of before
and it's scratching my own itch and
using that as the driver for choosing
which products I decide to build and
then launch into businesses. And that's
really the approach that I'm leaning
much more heavily into this year. And
I'm realizing now that taking this
approach of scratching my own itch to
drive the product ideas that I choose to
build, it's a lot more powerful than I
had even really understood earlier in my
career. And I'm realizing now that there
are some unique benefits to taking this
approach. And that's what I really want
to um talk to you about today because
they mean a lot to me in the in the work
that I'm doing at this desk every day
right now in 2025. So at a high level
there are three main factors at play
here. There's the mental health benefits
of this and I mean you know staying
happy, staying stressfree and using that
as your fuel to to produce and do your
best work and then there are the product
benefits meaning taking this approach
means you will build a better product
and then there is the success
probability. So, you know, we're all
trying to build something that could
lead to success, that could lead us to
the next step in our career, the next
level. I believe now that choosing to
scratch your own itch, gives you a
higher probability of reaching the
outcomes that you're hoping for. And
success might mean different things. I'm
going to talk about that uh in just a
minute, but first, let's unpack these a
little bit. Starting with probably the
most important, the mental health aspect
of this. you know, again, after years of
following that opportunistic approach
of, you know, searching for underserved
niches to build products for or knocking
on the door of businesses that I'm not
personally very experienced with, but
trying to talk to those business owners
or those customers to try to research
and discover pains that they might
experience that I could build a product
for, but I don't truly experience those.
So I've gone through those motions for
years and sometimes they they they led
to some level of product or business
success. But I also found that that
approach led me to layer on a lot of
pressure in different ways. Right there
there's the pressure of am I going about
this the right way? Am I talking to the
right people? Am I choosing the right
niches to serve? When I'm talking to a
customer, I'm constantly questioning is
what they're telling me actually true?
They might believe it to be true, but
are is it really going to be true when
they are asked to take out their wallet
and pay for a product? There's a lot of
lot of second-guessing that goes on in
in that approach. Right? The other
stress factor when you're taking that
opportunistic approach is, at least for
me, I'm constantly questioning, am I
wasting my time here? Am I just spinning
my wheels? I've done some videos about
this uh earlier on my channel that you
can check out, but you know that can be
pretty draining and and and can lead to
a lot of mental overhead. You know, just
think about like when you're sitting at
your desk and you're coding or you're
designing a product and you constantly
have this voice chirping in the back of
your head saying, "You're wasting your
time. You shouldn't be doing this. all
this effort, all all this time, all all
this all this energy that you're pouring
into this thing, it's not going to go
anywhere. You know, I think that when
you are taking the opportunistic
approach, it you have to reach a certain
level of of success in order for that to
be successful. So, that's the first
benefit of following a scratch my own
itch approach, right? I can get
satisfaction just by building something
for the fun of it. Now, the act of just
writing code or using AI to write code,
that's kind of cool, but that's not
actually where the fun is. What's
actually fun about building products is
I'm actually solving a need for myself
or I'm scratching I'm literally
scratching my own itch, right? And
coming out the other side with like a
little tool or a little utility or a
full product that I am excited to use
every single day. And it's better, like
far and away better than any other
product that I might buy. Not just
because I'm the one who built it, but
because it it actually serves my own
need. There is a immense satisfaction
that comes from that. Like I built this.
I put this together with my own hands
exactly the way that I want it. And that
is fun. That fires me up. I don't know
about you. I mean, it's like why do we
even do this, right? is why does any
product or any builder, any developer do
what they do? We want to have fun. We
want to build stuff. You get that from
scratching your own itch. You don't get
that from building. I mean, I I I had a
business very early in my career where I
was building websites for restaurants.
I'm not a restaurant owner, you know. I
um and uh I had no personal connection
to that to that world. I I didn't really
get a whole lot of satisfaction out of
making the best possible restaurant
website builder on the internet. You
know, the other aspect here when it
comes to mental health is scratching my
own itch allows me to keep my
expectations low. Right? Again, when
you're taking the opportunistic approach
and you have to find an a winning niche
product to go after or you have to find
a hot market trend to chase after, your
expectations are high. you you have to
set your expectations high otherwise
it's a waste of time right when I'm
building a product just to solve my own
need if I am the only customer who ever
uses the product that I'm building today
I'm happy with that I'm I'm actually
happy with that like right now this year
I'm currently building instrumental
components it's a Rails components
library for Ruby on Rails I hope that
some of the people who who watch my
channel here and and other people who
build with Rails will find it useful.
But to I'll be completely honest, I'm
building it for myself. I want to build
other products this year with Rails. And
this is a tool that helps me build
products much faster and uh and build
and lets me build them the way that I
want to build them, right? And if I am
the only person who ever ends up using
this product that I'm working on today,
I am actually very happy with that. like
it's totally worth my time because it's
not only scratching a a minor itch, it's
it's a product that I'm going to use in
my daily life every day when I'm
building products, you know. So, just
building for myself is a win. But I
actually also think that taking this
type of approach to formulating a
product actually gives you a much higher
chance of success in the market with
other customers and really hitting a
nerve and finding that that wave to ride
of of demand. And I'm going to get to
that at the end of this video where I
talked about the higher probability of
success. But again, even if I'm the only
customer, that's a win, too. Okay, let's
move on now to the product benefits.
Meaning by scratching your own itch, you
will build a better product than if you
were to just build a product for someone
else's itch. Right now, believe me, I
have built products for all sorts of
different customers, ranging from
customers who are so far away from who I
am as a person or as a professional to
other products that that did sort of
scratch my own itch. and and I've seen
um the differences in the actual quality
of the products. Now, I take a lot of
pride in my uh user interface skills and
my design skills and and my development
skills. So, I I feel like I can build a
pretty good product no matter what the
product is. But there is another level
to how effective a product is at
reaching that like product market fit,
right? When I'm scratching my own itch,
I'm building with conviction. You know,
I have strongly held beliefs around what
actually is the problem and why does
that problem matter? What is so
specifically painful about the problem?
And I have really strong opinions about
what I think the solution should be.
because I'm thinking about the solution
from the standpoint of like if I'm the
customer and I will be the customer for
this, here's how I want this product to
work and here's why I think it's better
than all the alternatives that I've ever
seen in the market. you know, that level
of conviction really leads to a much
better solution, a much better product,
and and again, like even if I'm the only
customer, it's like absolutely perfect
product market fit with myself. And that
does give you a higher likelihood of
success with reaching other customers
who really resonate and feel the same
way. I'll compare that to building a
product for a customer or for a problem
space that I don't personally identify
with or that I don't personally
experience that problem. You know, in
those situations, I really go deep into
customer research mode. I I do a lot of
customer interviews. I try to uh feel a
level of empathy for the customer. I try
to really understand where they're
coming from so that I can really
understand their experience with the
problem.
And I think I've I've gotten actually
pretty good with with that motion of
customer research and and interviewing
customers, but it's still not the same.
It doesn't reach the the potency that I
can feel when I'm scratching my own
itch, when I am customer number one, you
know. um there's still a lot of
guesswork and there have been multiple
times where I really think I have a good
grasp on what it is the customer is
feeling about the problem and and what
they truly want in a solution and I've
been quite frequently a little bit off
the mark with that because I don't
experience it myself and you know that
can happen in a number of ways right a
lot of times the customer or multiple
customers will point to a problem that
they all think is a problem but when it
comes down to it, it's not as painful as
they might uh express it or or I might
understand it to be. And even more often
is customers don't really know what the
true solution to the problem should be
or how the design should come together.
You know, that's what our job is as a
product designer. When when I'm
interviewing customers, I'm not actually
trying to ask them to give me the
solution. I'm just trying to understand
the problem so that I can come up with
the best possible solution. and that
it's it's very easy to reach a a a
disconnect there when you're not the
customer. But when I'm solving for
myself, I know exactly what the problem
is. I know exactly what I think the
solution should be and I go straight to
it. The next reason why it's possible to
build a much better product when you're
scratching your own itch is because it
can be truly unique. And these days
where the markets for products is so
hyper competitive, especially in SAS,
being unique, being different, being a
little weird is a huge huge benefit. And
and you know, I know that when I'm
scratching my own itch and I have that
conviction around um this is how I think
the the best possible solution should
be, it probably means that my solution
is different. It's probably a little
weird. It's a probably it's it's
probably kind of off-putting to a lot of
people who are used to to solving this
problem in a pretty different way.
What's leading to me to even have this
itch or have this problem or or the
desire to solve my own problem is that
I'm not satisfied with those solutions.
I I think that they get something wrong,
right? Um so I have a very different a
weird a unique idea for how I think it
should be solved. That's good. Now, I
used to again like comparing this to the
opportunistic approach. I used to take
the the stance of if it's too different,
if it's too weird, that's a warning sign
that like you're not going to tap into a
nerve in the market. Um, if nobody else
feels the same way as you, then you're,
you know, you're not going to hit it
right. But I feel the opposite now. When
I'm scratching my own edge, I'm looking
for what is different about this? What
is unique? Okay. So one more point on
why scratching your own itch can lead
you to building a better product is that
the road map paves itself. Prioritizing
is one of the hardest things when it
comes to building and shipping a
product. You know figuring out all right
I'm going to build this part first and
then I'm going to build this feature
then we're going to layer on that
feature and then we're going to
integrate all these features and then we
have a complete product to ship. That's
a specific road map. 1 2 3. And a lot of
my time every single day is shuffling
around the order of priority, figuring
out, okay, today I'm going to build this
piece, but I can't build this piece
until I build that piece. And that piece
is more important than this piece. So,
let's let's move that up in the priority
list. You know, that's that's what
product management is. And when you're
building and shipping your own products,
you're not only the product builder, but
you're also the product manager. And
that comes down to, you know, figuring
out the road map and figuring out the
priorities. Now, during the times that
I've built products for other customers
who are who who I don't identify with, I
did find that it was much harder to set
that priority order to set the road map.
you know, um there were times when I
just don't even know which features to
build next, and that's when I turned to
my customer interviews or there were
times when I have so many features that
I know I need to build that I know that
I've researched and customers have told
me are important, but I had a hard time
figuring out which ones are most
important to push into the road map in
which order. And I definitely found that
I chose to build and ship features that
I thought were most important, but it
wasn't until four or five features later
that I finally hit on the feature that
they actually cared about most. And
these are the kind of kinds of things
that customers won't just tell you. They
don't know. Again, they they might just
say like, "Yeah, that's important." Or,
"This is important." But at the end of
the day, like they don't really know
until they have the finished product in
their hand. When you're building for
yourself, again, all those road map
prioritization decisions are much
easier. They these decisions make
themselves. The road map paves itself.
Again, right now, I'm building
instrumental components at
instrumental.dev. And I know for exactly
which components, which parts of the
user experience of building with
components, which things are most
important to me as the user cuz I am
customer number one here. So, I'm making
sure I'm getting these things in first
and then I can start to think about
like, okay, we're we're in the home
stretch. I happen to be in the home
stretch now. So, now I'm starting to
think about like, okay, what do I need
to do to get this thing to launch and
then beyond? And then, you know, the
figuring out the pro the road map after
launch is is sort of another whole
story, probably a topic for another
whole video. But, okay, let's get into
the final section here, which is success
probability, right? I alluded to this a
little bit earlier. Here's the thing.
Novel products win. When your product is
truly unique and you can you can achieve
that uniqueness when you are scratching
your own itch because your idea, your
solution is a little bit weird, a little
bit different. That's a novel product.
You know, compare that to building just
another alternative to product, right?
if you're you're going after a a hot
market where there's lots of
competitors. Again, that's something
that I used to see as a as a big
benefit. In some ways, it still is, I
think, where where it's okay where you
can look at a market and say like, okay,
I know that there are a lot of tools
here. I know that there are a lot of
customers buying those tools. That is
definitely a signal that tells me
there's market activity here. So, it is
worth exploring like can I come into
this market and offer a new alternative
to those existing solutions. That's a
valid approach. And since it is an
active maybe a hot market, you probably
are going to pick up some customers who
who are just kind of riding in this
wave. They're going to choose yours over
the many other competitors in the
market. That's great, but you're also
going to constantly be battling churn.
It's going to be a constant battle of
your product against all the other
alternative to your product. and your
product is just another one in a long
line of competitors and they all more or
less do the same thing with maybe
slightly different designs or or
interfaces or pricing or whatever it
might be. Again, like in in that kind of
situation, every new customer, this the
cell is convincing them that your
product is a little bit better and that
it's worth the effort for them to
switch. And if your product doesn't
fully nail it, then they're just easily
gonna, you know, cancel your product and
move on to the next one, right? Compare
that to a truly novel product. Something
that's a little bit weird, a little bit
different, takes a high conviction,
takes a very opinionated approach to
solving a a very specific problem.
That's what happens when I'm scratching
my own itch. What that does is it
produces raving fans, right? That's how
you produce customers who will never
leave your product. No matter what the
other competitors are doing, they are
just so bought in to your way, your
world view, how you see the problem, how
you've solved the problem that they are
just ecstatic to use that every day. I
can point to a small handful of products
that I feel that way about. The other
thing about this is that your customers
who are raving fans, they are going to
go annoy all of their friends until they
finally convince them that they too need
to use your product because it's that
good. Like I am not satisfied until I
convince uh 10 people around me that um
this product that means so much to me
personally um every single day uh they
need to feel that too. like it it like
humans just can't help but try to push
products onto one another um when they
feel that deeply about that. You don't
get that level of fire from your
customers when um you're just another
alternative to in a in a crowded market.
You get that fire when you take a a
backwards stance on a on a idea. And you
know, maybe that means that it's a it's
a higher bar to reach in terms of
educating a market or or telling the
market that like, hey, this different
way of um exists or or hey, let's open
our minds to trying out a different way
of looking at this, but it can really be
worth it. Okay. Another reason why you
have a higher probability or higher
likelihood of success when you are
scratching your own itch is that you'll
stick with it. Look, success in
business, especially success in in a
products business is about playing the
long game. And the long game means like,
you know, you'll get a few customers up
front, then you'll then you'll get a few
more customers. It'll be a slow, steady
ramp up. It almost never happens to see
that hockey stick growth. That's why
they call it the the long slow SAS ramp
of death, right? Because because you
just got to stay with it for so so long.
Most products, especially bootstrapped
products, fail not because the product
wasn't good or not because they couldn't
find any customers. More often, they
failed because the founder just didn't
stick with it. The founder got bored,
the founder uh got burned out. Maybe the
the founder moved on to another shiny
object. These things all happen when you
don't have a product that you can
naturally,
organically, personally just stick with
for a very, very long time. If you're
scratching your own itch, I wouldn't say
it's completely immune to those
challenges of sticking with it for the
long term, but it's much more resistant.
Right? If I'm scratching my own itch,
and especially if it's a product that I
am actually personally using every
single day in my work, then I'm much
much more likely to stick with it and
keep tinkering with it and keep making
it a little bit better and a little bit
better. And I'm I'm more than happy to
talk to customers about it. sales calls
don't even feel like sales calls. They
feel like I'm talking to friends because
they experience the same problems and
pains that I do, you know? So, like it's
it's fun for me to talk to customers to
do customer support for people who are
using my product that I personally use
and love every day. Um, and I can I can
talk much more passionately about it.
and and that leads to better marketing,
you know, because it's more genuine,
it's more authentic, and of course, as I
talked about earlier, it's a much better
product, higher likelihood of product
market fit because it has that
conviction. Last point that I'll make
here is that by scratching your own
itch, you have a higher likelihood of
stumbling into success. Here's what I
mean by that. Your product idea today,
even if you're scratching your own itch,
it might not be it. It might not be the
one where you find that breakaway
success, but by being in motion, by
building products that scratch your own
itch, that gives you the chance to
stumble in to another itch. It's it
gives you a chance to stumble into
another problem, another space that you
didn't quite know existed earlier, but
now now you're starting to feel
something. Now you're starting to sense
something, and maybe that one is the
product that could be it for you. It
gives you that sort of like
serendipitous
uh chance to to stumble into something,
stumble into the a seed of an idea. So
start with an itch, find another itch,
find another itch, and and that could
lead to the winning product. And
remember, at the end of the day, even if
whatever product you build, whatever
whatever itch you're looking to scratch,
even if no one else feels that or
experiences that, at the end of the day,
you're building something for yourself.
you're solving your own problem and that
is a win in itself. That's why I'm
scratching my own itch this year with
the products that I choose to build and
ship. If you resonated with what I
talked about here, I also feel really
strongly about the idea of bootstrapping
my own products, meaning self-funding,
uh, using my skills as a product
designer, product developer to build and
ship and sell and grow my own products
without the need to take investment
money or, you know, work on a runway and
be unprofitable. If those kind of ideas
uh resonate with you, then I invite you
to in to watch this other video all
about bootstrapping and what I think it
actually means to bootstrap a business
in 2025. Check that out. I'll see you
there. And if you have any questions or
anything, leave them in the comments.
I'll get right back to you. Thanks for
watching.